Akash Saha

PhD Lab, Third Floor, IEOR Building IIT Bombay, Mumbai, India 400076

Career Objective

A researcher with 5+ years of experience in working with machine learning models seeking a position to utilize my knowledge and gain professional experience while being resourceful, innovative and analytical. My primary research theme is to develop efficient optimization methods and algorithms for machine learning problems. This involves investigation of both the theoretical and practical aspects of optimization methodologies. I am also interested in looking into applications of machine learning and deep learning in relatively less explored directions.

Email: akashsaha@iitb.ac.in

Mobile: +91-9007603810

EDUCATION

PhDMumbai, India Industrial Engineering and Operations Research (IEOR), IIT Bombay January 2018 - Ongoing Master of Science Roorkee, India Industrial Mathematics & Informatics, IIT Roorkee; CGPA: 9.104/10 July 2012 - May 2014 Bachelor of Science Kolkata, India Mathematics Honours, Jadavpur University; Percentage: 78.25% July 2009 - June 2012 Higher Secondary Examination (10+2) West Bengal, India Julien Day School, ISC Examination, New Delhi; Percentage: 91.14% June 2007 - May 2009 Secondary Examination (10) West Bengal, India Julien Day School, ICSE Examination, New Delhi; Percentage: 94.71% May 2007

Research Interests

• Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Explainability of learning models, Optimization Techniques.

Research Area

Theory and algorithms for Kernel-based Learning Problems

Supervisor: Prof. P. Balamurugan

- Machine learning methods which can handle functional features can open up plenty of new areas of application, where the flexibility of functional and infinite-dimensional spaces would enable us to achieve significantly better performance while managing huge amounts of training data.
- Kernel based leaning algorithms have been a popular tool in supervised learning problems, we are working on an extension to operator-valued kernels for learning problems in a functional setting.
- Future work involves establishing connections to deep learning in various aspects of the algorithm.

Publications

• Saha, A. and Balamurugan, P., "Learning with Operator-valued Kernels in Reproducing Kernel Krein Spaces." Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS), vol. 33, 2020. Accepted for Oral Presentation with acceptance rate: 1.1% (105/9454).

SUMMER SCHOOL/WORKSHOPS

- Participated in the LinkedIn-MSR-IISc Workshop on "Fairness, Accountability, Transparency and Ethics in Machine Learning" at IISc, Bangalore from January 9 10, 2020.
- Attended International Centre for Theoretical Sciences (ICTS) program on "Statistical Physics of Machine Learning" held in ICTS, Bangalore from January 6 10, 2020.
- Attended "Indo-French Centre for Applied Mathematics (IFCAM) summer school workshop on Mathematics for Data Science" at IISc, Bangalore from July 15 27, 2019.

Research Internship

Research Intern Bengaluru, India

Computational and Statistical Physics Lab, Indian Institute of Science

May 2013 - July 2013

• Worked on spectral distribution of random matrices under the supervision of Prof. V. Murugesan

KEY COURSES

Machine Learning, Optimization Techniques, Stochastic Models, Deep Learning, Decision Analysis and Game Theory, IEOR for Health Care, Integer Programming, OR Applications in Infrastructural and Service Sectors, Real & Complex Analysis...

Projects

- Generating images from CIFAR10.
- Using deep learning for PAN & AADHAR card identification.
- Implementing various heuristics for TSP vs Concorde Solver.
- A heuristic for Wavelength Division Multiplexing Problem.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant IIT Bombay January 2018 - Ongoing

IEOR Department Courses

- IE 663: Advanced Topics in Deep Learning.
- IE 643: Deep Learning Theory and Practice.
- IE 614: Linear Systems.
- IE 503: Operation Analysis.

Assistant Professor Telangana, India

Rajiv Gandhi University of Knowledge Technologies, Basar

July 2014 - December 2017

• Courses taught: Discrete Mathematics, Numerical Methods, Probability & Statistics, Probability and Stochastic Processes, Engineering Mathematics.

SKILL SET

- **Programming Languages:** Python, C++, C
- Optimization Solvers: CPLEX, AMPL, Gurobi
- Analytical Tools: Microsoft Excel
- Computaional/Utility Tools: MATLAB, R, LATEX

MOOC CERTIFICATIONS

NPTEL Online Certification:

- Introduction to Data Analytics
- Introduction to Cryptology

Extra Curricular Activities

- Won Table Tennis PG General Championship for IEOR Department [2019 20].
- Placement Representative of Mathematics Department, IIT Roorkee [2013-14].

References

Prof. P. Balamurugan

IEOR, IIT Bombay

balamurugan.palaniappan@iitb.ac.in

(More references can be provided on request.)